<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Crittergo</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2014-02-15T17:34:45-08:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Crittergo</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rat]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/rat/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/rat</id>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rat-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rats are one of the more atypical but neat small rodents that you can have as a pet. They are perfect for young children, and they come in a wide variety of color coats and temperaments. Typically, they live for between one and a half to two and a half years if they are cared for well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most other small rodents, rats are very social creatures. You should consider having at least two rats at any given time to prevent loneliness. When it comes to providing a living area for your rats, they should have a medium to large cage with bedding made from recycled paper or wood 
chips that are not pine or cedar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rats have a rather specialized diet that needs to be high in protein. There are “rat blocks” that are sold by various pet care companies that provide high protein as well as a large amount of vitamins and nutrients that will keep your rat healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should make sure that your rat has ample place to run around so that they do not become bored and lethargic. They enjoy playing with toys and 
tunneling in their bedding. You should also consider giving your rat man-made tunnels that they can use to avoid direct light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest dangers to the health of a rat is a cold. They are susceptible to them and if left untreated, they can be fatal. On the other end of the spectrum, rats are likely to be harmed by excessive amounts of heat, and should be kept in a moderately temperate room. If your rat becomes unusually lethargic, they should be examined by a vet, though there is not a great deal that they can do to treat an injured animal of this size.Rats require hard chewing blocks in order to keep their teeth from growing 
too large or creating dental problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While rats are small, and consequently so are their droppings, they need to have their cage or living space cleaned weekly. This will prevent diseases spreading between the two rats and allow them to live comfortably and cleanly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.ratcare.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/rat/&quot;&gt;Rat&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Iguana]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/reptiles/iguana/"/>
  <id>/reptiles/iguana</id>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/iguana-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iguanas can be a fun and relatively low key pet option. However, they can also be fairly expensive, especially when buying initial supplies for the pet. Getting a new iguana can be very exciting, but it’s important to leave the iguana alone for a few weeks after brining it home, in order for it to adjust properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iguanas should have a cage or other type of enclosure. Some iguana owners allow their iguanas to have free range of the home, but if this is your first time owning an iguana, it’s best to have it in a cage at first. Iguanas can grow very large, and the cage should be at least twice the length of the iguana, and owners may need to get a larger cage as the iguana grows. The cage should be lined with newspapers, paper towels, or carpet. There should also be climbing structures or shelves so the iguana can climb and explore. Iguana also needs to have regular exposure to natural sunlight in addition to a heat lamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to general iguana food that can be purchased at a pet store, iguanas also need fruits and vegetables. Iguanas should be fed at least once per day, and more for iguanas that have larger appetites. Fresh water should also be easily accessible, and you can spray water onto the iguana’s food in order to ensure it’s drinking enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure not to handle the iguana during the first few weeks of having it. As the iguana gets used to his new surroundings, you can handle it more and more, and it will become more tame. Having it out of the cage, under close supervision, is alright once he’s gotten used to his home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep the iguana healthy, regular cleaning is necessary. The iguana owner should also use antibacterial soap to thoroughly clean his or her hands after feeding or otherwise handling the iguana. The cage should be cleaned regularly, and the bedding should be removed. It’s a good idea to invest in a disinfectant that will sterilize the cage during regular cleanings. Remove the iguana while cleaning the cage. Regular cleaning will help avoid parasites and other diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, iguanas are fairly clean, but you should regularly give your iguana a bath to clean off food or feces on the animal. You can purchase a large tub to use for a bath, and it should be filled with warm water. Soap should never be used. The iguana cage should also be lightly sprayed with water from a spray bottle on a daily basis, to keep the habitat moist.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reptiles/iguana/&quot;&gt;Iguana&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hedgehog]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/hedgehog/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/hedgehog</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hedgehog-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedgehogs are relatively small, insect-eating rodents that can make great pets if they have a dedicated owner. While many people will be turned away by the presence of their quills, hedgehogs are able to be petted safely, without any risk of injury to you or them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shelter that you need to provide for your hedgehog will need to be very large to accommodate their active lifestyle. You should have a multi-tiered cage that has a two square feet base and at least two feet high. They require a great deal of space to move about. The bottom of their cage, usually a wire cage, should not be covered solely by wood chip bedding. They should have some sort of loose cloth such as fleece that they can wrap themselves in if they feel cold, as they are very sensitive to changes in temperature. For the most part, hedgehogs do not like to share their habitat with other hedgehogs and should be kept as solo pets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedgehogs have unusual dietary requirements that must be met if they are to live a healthy life. While they can be fed dry cat food with a high protein and vitamin D content, they can also subsist on freeze-dried beetles. Make sure the food bowl is wide enough that the hedgehog will not turn it over while they are attempting to eat. Pet shops carry ceramic bowls that are extra wide and have a firm base that are perfect for 
hedgehogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, you can allow your hedgehog out of its cage to get To help them get exercise, you can use pet barriers to block off a room so exercise in a safe indoor area. They usually do not like to be placed into balls, depending on their temperament, and they prefer open spaces to their cage, no matter how large it may be, that they can frolic safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most unique problem facing hedgehogs is obesity. You must make sure that they have adequate space to move around in the cage. Also, you must be sure that you regulate their diet so that they do not eat too much food. If your hedgehog is unable to fold into a ball, then you should consult a veterinarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other pet, you should change the bedding in your hedgehog’s cage every week. Since they prefer cloth material, you should clean any droppings out of the cage daily, and be prepared to change the bedding at any time. You can wash the fleece in a washing machine or by hand, using only dish soap and hot water to prevent skin irritation. When it comes to cleaning the base of the cage, you should use hot water and dish soap in conjunction with a scrubbing brush for maximum cleanliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.hedgehogclub.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/hedgehog/&quot;&gt;Hedgehog&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guinea Pig]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/guinea-pig/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/guinea-pig</id>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/guinea-pig-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most loving and rewarding pets that you can own is a Guinea Pig. They are quiet, easy to care for, and can provide companionship for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary shelter that you can provide for a Guinea Pig is a large cage with soft bedding. However, many pet owners prefer to let their Guinea Pigs roam around their home, either freely or inside a play ball. Certain precautions must be taken to ensure that your pet does not wander into any hazardous areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you will primarily feed a Guinea Pig manufactured food, you can always supplement their diet with vegetables such as carrots to make sure that they receive the proper amount of nutrients and vitamins to allow them to live a long, healthy life. One of the treats that you can feed Guinea Pigs is timothy hay, a healthy grass that allows them to keep their teeth healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Guinea Pigs will spend the majority of their day in an area of the cage that is out of direct sight. Some Guinea Pigs will remain nocturnal when you keep them and should be given a dark shelter. For this reason you need to make sure that you pay attention to when your pet is most active, and allow them to wander out of the cage freely under supervision, or inside a ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most other small animals, you need to make sure that your Guinea Pig is drinking sufficient amounts of water. This is most noticeable in their droppings, which should be small and relatively hard. If they experience wetness in their hindquarters or have any noticeable discharge, then they 
need to be taken to a vet immediately for examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleaning a Guinea Pig’s fur is simple because they enjoy water, for the most part. However, this is discouraged in the winter or in a cold environment. They must be bathed in warm water to regulate their body temperature. Also, since they frequently defecate, it is smart to clean their cage or primary area before you can smell it. Try not to put a clean Guinea Pig into a dirty area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;*Source: http://www.aspca.org *&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/guinea-pig/&quot;&gt;Guinea Pig&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gerbil]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/gerbil/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/gerbil</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gerbil-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerbils are one of the most active and lovable small rodents that you can keep as a pet. That also means that they can be some of the most troublesome to keep in a cage. However, if you manage to give them a good home, then your gerbil can live for between three and four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other small rodents, gerbils are very social animals and you should at least consider keeping several of them together. However, it is a bad idea 
to keep males and females together because they will breed quickly. You can house gerbils in a wire cage or a glass aquarium. It needs to be kept away from direct light or cold air to avoid sickness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerbils tend to eat seeds as a main source of food. You can buy a pre-mixed blend of food at any pet store that will consist of seed, pellets, and dried vegetables. You can feed gerbils small amounts of fresh fruits and vegetables. Also, they enjoy sunflower seeds as a snack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not advised to let your gerbils out of their cage and into the open unless you are absolutely sure that the area is escape proof. Gerbils are very frisky, and they can squeeze into small areas and become lost. Another great way to make sure that your gerbil gets exercise is by putting them in a small exercise ball and letting them loose around your home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most gerbils should be taken to a veterinarian once a year for examination. One of the biggest dangers facing gerbils is actually diarrhea and dehydration. This can be prevented by providing adequate water and fiber-rich foods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any pet that is kept in a cage, you should change the bedding of your gerbil’s habitat every week, with daily removal of droppings. It is important that your pets develop a sense of familiarity with you. This can be achieved by handling them safely, and often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt; *Source: http://www.aspca.org *&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/gerbil/&quot;&gt;Gerbil&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ferret]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/ferret/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/ferret</id>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ferret-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferrets are some of the most beautiful and interesting small, domesticated rodents. They come in a wide variety of colors including brown, red, white, and gold. They typically live between six and eight years, and require a bit of special care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since ferrets are some of the most active and playful small rodents, they need a great deal of space to move around. As such, they should not be caged for long periods of time, and when they are, they need a cage that has plenty of tubes and hiding spaces to keep themselves entertained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since ferrets are some of the most active and playful small rodents, they need a great deal of space to move around. As such, they should not be caged for long periods of time, and when they are, they need a cage that has plenty of tubes and hiding spaces to keep themselves entertained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferrets are one of the most playful small rodents. They need to have a great deal of time to run around every day or they will get restless and start chewing on anything that they can find. This can cause injuries and aggravation. So, it is important to have a small rodent ball that you can put your ferret into so that they can roll around safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most dangerous illness that can face a ferret is intestinal obstruction. This happens when they chew on soft plastic pieces such as their food bowl, and swallow it, creating a blockage that is often fatal. Also, you may want to consider de-scenting your ferret for practical reasons, unless you are breeding your ferret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should change your ferret’s bedding completely at least once a week, with daily removals of wet or messy bedding. Also, it is possible to litter train ferrets since they are such intelligent animals. Not only will this give them a cleaner habitat, but it will ensure that they live a longer, healthier life. Not to mention, it is a neat trick that you can show your friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/ferret/&quot;&gt;Ferret&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chipmunk]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/chipmunk/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/chipmunk</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/chipmunk-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siberian chipmunks are fun, active critters that can be a bit of a handful to raise because of their high energy. They are small, typically between five and six inches in length, and only weigh about 2-3 ounces. Despite their small size and active lifestyle, Siberian chipmunks can live for up to ten years if they are treated properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The housing for a Siberian chipmunk is one of the more complicated facets of owning a chipmunk. They should have a multi-level wire cage. The bars should be less than a half inch apart to prevent them from escaping from the habitat.
While they are small animals, the cage should measure 12x24x18 inches at minimum. This will allow them to have plenty of room to run around, especially considering that it is not recommended that you allow them to run around your home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another neat idea for a chipmunk housing unit is to build a small wooden enclosure that is about the size of a birdhouse: 6x6x8 inches for example. This will give them the sense of being in an outdoors area while providing a dark place within their cage.The bedding in their habitat should consist of a thick assortment of wood chips that can be burrowed in while providing a soft landing area for when 
they tumble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main part of a Siberian chipmunk’s diet should consist of rodent diet pellets that are high in fiber and protein. Chipmunks should also be fed a large assortment of vegetables, fruits, and nuts such as pecans, peanuts, apples, grapes, and broccoli. Siberian chipmunks require fresh water to be added to their bottle daily. This should be cleaned at least once every two weeks with a pipe brush and hot water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, Siberian chipmunks will be able to get as much exercise as they need in their cage as long as you provide them with a wheel and a large enough cage. You should also purchase several toys to keep your chipmunk engaged and playful such as logs and balls that they can roll through their bedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the health concerns for Siberian chipmunks is the length of their nails. You should take your chipmunk to a vet at least once a year, and during that time they should have their nails trimmed to an acceptable level.Another consideration for Siberian chipmunk health is oral care. You should provide plenty of chewing toys so that they can cull their teeth, which will prevent oral decay and a variety of other ailments. You should watch for signs of a cold such as runny eyes and coughing. This can lead to complications of the respiratory system, which is one of the leading causes of death in chipmunks besides old age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can give a Siberian chipmunk a sponge bath if they become too dirty from walking through soiled bedding. Use only warm water and be extremely gentle. You should change the bedding of the cage once a week and clean the bottom of the cage at the same time. To do this, you should use only hot water and a scrub brush so that there are no adverse reactions to cleaning chemicals. By following these simple tips, you can extend the life of your Siberian chipmunk by years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.sandsexoticanimals.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/chipmunk/&quot;&gt;Chipmunk&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chinchilla]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/chinchilla/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/chinchilla</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/chinchilla-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinchillas are a medium-sized rodent, between ten and twelve inches in length, and are famous for their love of burrowing and hiding in their habitats. They make great pets because they are soft, social, and rarely bite. Aside from their beauty, they can live as long as twenty years if they receive the right kind of care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shelter that you are going to want to give your chinchilla is similar to other small rodents in the sense that you should provide a wire cage with a plastic basin. However, it must be larger than the typical rodent cage and should measure somewhere around 2 feet by 1 ½ feet by 2 feet. They need a cage where they can have room to run, jump, and hide themselves as well as their toys. Like other small animals, they benefit from having bedding such as pine chips on the bottom of their cage to catch waste and soften their landings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can feed chinchillas a blend of pellets specially made for chinchillas that is sold in any pet store. Also, chinchillas enjoy timothy hay and other small animal-safe grasses. It is important to keep a feeder of fresh, temperate water in their cage at all times. Chinchillas need to drink frequently, and should have their bottles cleaned regularly. You can clean their bottles by using hot water and a small amount of dish soap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since chinchillas tend to become very attached to their owners or other chinchillas in their habitat, you should dedicate time every day to interacting and playing with your chinchilla. They are fragile animals, but they enjoy running, climbing, and jumping.You can put your chinchilla in a small rodent ball, one foot in circumference, and allow them to roam around a safe area. Chinchillas can also roam freely, but you must be sure that the area is devoid of cubbies or other areas where they can become lost or trapped. You can buy several mesh gates that will allow you to cordon off a room 
for your chinchilla to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are cared for properly, chinchillas can live an incredibly long life for a rodent. This requires a yearly checkup with a veterinarian to look for any possible anomalies. One of the most common injuries that chinchillas can suffer is a broken bone in their back foot that can result from rough play or fighting with other chinchillas. By keeping a thick layer of soft bedding, you can reduce the risk of this happening. Another consideration for chinchillas’ health is gastrointestinal problems that can result from an improper diet. If your chinchilla seems unusually lethargic or is laying down much more than usual, they should be taken to a vet immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things that you can do for your chinchilla is to give them a clean environment. Make sure that you remove droppings and wet bedding daily, and completely replace the bedding once every week. It is important to clean the bottom of the basin out using hot water and hypoallergenic dish soap such as Dawn that will not provoke adverse skin reactions. Use a scrub brush to get a complete cleaning experience. You can give your chinchilla a bath if they begin to smell badly, but be sure to use temperate water rather than hot or cold water because they are very sensitive to changes in temperature. To bathe them, use a small amount of water and consider putting your chinchilla in a colander or sieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.chinchillacare.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/chinchilla/&quot;&gt;Chinchilla&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bearded Dragon]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/reptiles/bearded-dragon/"/>
  <id>/reptiles/bearded-dragon</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bearded-dragon-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons are a fun, entertaining type of reptile to have as a pet, though they do require special equipment and some extra attention compared to many other types of reptiles. However, they are also fairly active, and are relatively easy to tame, making them enjoyable pets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons require fairly large tanks; a 40 gallon tank is the smallest acceptable size for a single beaded dragon, and if you have more than one, they should have a bigger tank. It’s also necessary to have a screen lid to cover the top of the lid. The cage should be lined with paper towels or paper, though sand, wood shavings, and similar products should be avoided, as the animal may eat them. The cage should also be complete with rocks and things to hide in. Most importantly, beaded dragons need exposure to heat lamps, and special UVA/UVB radiation lamps for reptiles can be purchased. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons should have water provided at all times. Their diet consists of both insects and vegetables. They typically eat crickets or mealworms, and younger bearded dragons should be fed more frequently, twice each day. Adults can be fed just once each day. Vegetables such as carrots, green beans, and peas can also be fed to bearded dragons .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons can be handled regularly by their owners. Though they don’t need excessive regular attention, bearded dragons can be handled in order to give them extra activity. Some owners get leashes for bearded dragons so that they can explore without worry that they’ll get away. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons may get dehydrated, so it’s important to keep water readily available. Bearded dragons with sunken eyes or wrinkled skin are likely dehydrated. Additional water or a diluted sports drink can be administered with an eye dropper if they initially refuse water. Bearded dragons also may 
experience droopy eyes, which is often caused by kidney problems. A bearded dragon with droopy eyes should see a vet right away for treatment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though bearded dragons do not require extensive grooming, their nails may get long and extremely sharp. Owners can use a nail clipper and trip the tips of the nails, being careful not to trim too deeply. Nails should be trimmed no more than once every month.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reptiles/bearded-dragon/&quot;&gt;Bearded Dragon&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rabbit]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/rabbit/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/rabbit</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-14T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rabbit-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the cutest and most engaging small animals that you can own is a rabbit. Domesticated rabbits vary in looks and personality, 
each with their own benefits. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, you should keep your rabbit at home in a large, comfortable cage with a great deal of soft bedding for them to 
nuzzle. They should always be kept indoors, as they are social animals and can be literally driven to a heart attack if they see a predator coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of a domesticated rabbit’s diet should come from grasses and timothy hay. These nutritious grasses are crucial to keep your rabbit’s digestive system and teeth healthy. If you are raising your rabbit from a young age, then for the first year you should give them a great deal of fresh, plain rabbit pellets. It is also important to keep an ample supply of water in a dish or a feeder, depending on which one your rabbit prefers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your rabbit will need a large amount of space to run around and frolic, but again this needs to be indoors only. You need to rabbit-proof the area to prevent them from chewing paper or electrical wires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you are keeping a single rabbit, then you should consider spaying and neutering them to prevent certain types of cancer from 
forming. Typically, you should take your rabbit for a checkup once every year. Like other small rodents, if you notice that your rabbit is not moving its bowels regularly, then you should take it to the vet immediately to check for obstruction. This is prevalent in small animals, like rabbits, that like to chew household materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should remove all of the soiled bedding from your rabbit’s cage every single day, with a full cleaning occurring once a week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see your rabbit eating their own feces, do not be concerned. This is a normal activity that is used to help regulate their bowels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rabbits should be brushed often to help maintain their fur. When picking your rabbit up, support its rear as well as its head.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/rabbit/&quot;&gt;Rabbit&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 14, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chameleon]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/reptiles/chameleon/"/>
  <id>/reptiles/chameleon</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-14T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/chameleon-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people like the idea of a chameleon as a pet due to their ability to change colors. 
Chameleons are hardy, and don’t require a great deal of care. However, they aren’t 
particularly playful or cuddly, and they should not be handled regularly, so for pet owners 
who want more interaction, they aren’t the best choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chameleons need fairly large aquariums that are well ventilated; ideally made out 
of screen as opposed to glass. The cage should be lined with a light bedding, like 
newspaper or paper towels. Things like sand or gravel are not good ideas, as the 
chameleons may eat it and have health problems. A heat lamp is also required for 
chameleons. It’s important for the cage to contain live plants, branches, and other 
similar item so the chameleons are able to climb and exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chameleons can eat a wide range of different types of foods, from insects such as 
crickets or worms, to various plants, including lettuce, flowering plants, dandelion leaves, 
and carrots. Insects that are too large could be difficult to digest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chameleons can become stressed if they are handled too much. However, while 
cleaning the cage, owners can give chameleons time to explore and climb. A small, 
enclosed, alternate cage can be used to give the chameleon more space during 
cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chameleons are prone to getting dehydrated, so it’s a good idea to regularly mist the 
cage with a water bottle to keep the enclosure moist. A dehydrated chameleon may 
have closed or sunken eyes. Be sure the chameleon is getting regular water. By misting 
regularly, you can ensure your chameleon has plenty of water, as misting allows for 
water droplets to form on the plants in the cage for the chameleon to drink. A clean 
spray bottle is the easiest way to keep water in the cage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chameleons do not require any significant cleaning or groom, and in fact, handling of &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;chameleons should be limited. They are extremely low maintenance in this respect.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reptiles/chameleon/&quot;&gt;Chameleon&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 14, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cats]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/cats/cat/"/>
  <id>/cats/cat</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-14T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cat-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cat is a great option for anyone looking for a pet that is both fun and friendly, yet requires 
relatively low care. While cats certainly need love and attention, in addition to food, water, 
and their litter boxes regularly cleaned, they are also quite independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats do not require any specific types of shelter, though many cat owners purchase various “cat condos” or similar products that serve as a place for cats to nap and play. Such products often include a scratching component as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats typically can be fed either wet or dry cat food, and should always have plenty of fresh water available. Cat treats can also be incorporated, though they should be limited to ensure your cat doesn’t gain too much weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kittens are often full of energy and enjoy playing, and keeping plenty of toys available will ensure the cat does a lot of playing to burn off energy. Cats who spend time outdoors likely get more exercise than indoor cats. To ensure your cat stays healthy and doesn’t gain too much weight, do not overfeed and take time each day to play with your cat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats are generally quite healthy, but be sure to check with a vet if you notice anything out of the ordinary. Hairballs can be a common problem,, but there are many products that can be purchased to avoid them. As cats age, there are several health problems that can take place, so pay special attention to aging cats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats are fairly self-sufficient when it comes to grooming. Short haired cats require minimal grooming, though long haired cats can be brushed on occasions to reduce shedding. Brushing can also help lower the risk of your cat experiencing hairballs.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/cats/cat/&quot;&gt;Cats&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 14, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hamster]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/hamster/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/hamster</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-11T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hamster-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to own a small pet, a hamster is a good place to start. They require minimal care when in a comfortable environment. They are nocturnal and prefer to live alone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many styles of shelter for your hamster, from cages, aquariums, to intricate habitats with a number of tubes to crawl through. Once you’ve chosen the a type of housing, you will need to fill it with bedding to keep the environment dry and keep odor under control.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Store-bought hamster foods include a mixture of seeds and grains. For added variety, you can supplement with fresh nuts, fruits and vegetables a couple times a week. Avoid onions, candy, chocolate, large beans, rhubarb or raw potatoes. Always have have plenty of fresh water in a suspended rodent drinking bottle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamsters like to burrow and exercise. A shelter with tubes and spaces to hide in and a wheel to run around will keep your hamster happy and healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While hamsters are normally quite hardy, small injuries or illnesses can complicate quickly. If you find signs such as loss of appetite, sneezing, discharge from the nose or eyes, wheezing, wetness around the tail, hair loss, or diarrhea you should consider a trip to the vet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your hamster cage will require touching up or bedding replacement. If you notice stronger odors, consider cleaning more frequently. 
Unless your hamster has something sticky in its fur, it should never have a bath in water. Fill a small bowl with chinchilla bath sand made from volcanic ash and place it in the cage. The hamster will instinctively roll around in it to clean itself off. Make sure that the sand you purchase is dust-free to prevent respiratory issues. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/hamster/&quot;&gt;Hamster&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 11, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
