<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Crittergo</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2014-02-16T10:04:25-08:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Crittergo</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Turtle]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/reptiles/turtle/"/>
  <id>/reptiles/turtle</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/turtle-aqua-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turtles may appear to be a relatively low key pet, but there are several factors to consider before adoption one. Turtles should, like other reptiles, carry salmonella, and should not be kept as pets with young children, seniors, or those especially susceptible for disease. Turtles can also live a very long time, which should be kept in mind when selecting a pet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turtles should be kept in a large tank, at least 30-40 gallons. There should be areas of water and land for the turtle to explore, and turtles should also have a heat lamp. The cage itself should be lined with bedding or other type of liner cage should also have some sort of shelter within the tank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turtles eat both protein and fruits and vegetables. Younger turtles need to be fed more frequently, at least every day, and older turtles can be fed 3-4 times each week. Turtles should be fed worms, slugs, or crickets in addition to fruits and vegetables. Turtles should also have fresh water at all times.
##Activity/Exercise &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turtles typically keep to themselves and aren’t very active. In fact, it’s not a good idea to remove the turtle from her cage very much, as the rapid changes in temperature can be bad for her. Turtles typically hibernate for 10-20 weeks during the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a healthy environment for a turtle is essential to keeping them healthy. Be sure to clean the cage regularly, and to find out the specific habitat requirements for your breed of turtle. It’s also important to be especially careful about the spread of salmonella with turtles, as the disease can also affect the turtles as well. Keeping the cage clean is the best way to prevent turtles from getting infected. To clean the cage, remove the liner and everything else, then fill the cage with warm water and a small amount of dishwashing detergent. It’s a good idea to use gloves, then scrub the cage thoroughly before rinsing it out and replacing the bedding and other components of the cage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grooming for turtles is minimal. If the turtle’s shell or body is dirty from something in the cage, you can assist with cleaning, but generally regularly cleaning of the cage will prevent this from being a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reptiles/turtle/&quot;&gt;Turtle&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sugar Glider]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/sugar-glider/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/sugar-glider</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sugarglider-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sugar gliders are an exotic pet that can be rather difficult, yet rewarding to own. They have some particular needs, but are relatively easy to care for if you know some basic information. They can be your companions for about twelve to fifteen years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to successfully house a sugar glider you will need a rather large cage. At the bare minimum, they need a cage that is 30x18x36 inches in size; the taller the better. They need ample room to jump and glide in order to be happy.The bottom of their cage needs to be covered in wood chips or similar soft bedding to catch droppings and keep the cage dry. The best type of bedding for sugar gliders is pine chips, for its pleasant aroma and easiness to clean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sugar gliders enjoy a diet that is rich in fruits and vegetables to provide them with all of the energy that they need to be active. In particular, you should treat them to citrus fruits, bananas, softened carrots, and bits of corn. They also require a high amount of protein in their diet that can be fulfilled by crickets, dry pellets, or even turkey food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part about sugar gliders is that they are so naturally active that you do not need to be an active part in their exercise. They run, jump, and glide all on their own. They just need the amount of required space in order to perform these activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since they are naturally nocturnal animals, if you notice that they are not active during the night or especially active during the day, you should have them examined by a veterinarian. They are companionate animals that need to have attention from their owner in order to remain healthy. Otherwise, they can become sulky and withdrawn, which can have physical symptoms. One of the biggest dangers for sugar gliders is the flight membrane from their wrist to their ankles. It can become damaged or torn during activities, and while this is rare, it requires immediate attention from a professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since they can be somewhat messy when it comes to their droppings, you will need to clean their cage completely twice a week. This involves using a bleach and water mixture to clean every level of the multi-tiered cage to remove feces and urine from the bars where they tend to sit. When the bedding is removed, clean the bottom of the cage with a ½ cup to 1 gallon ratio of bleach and water using a scrubbing brush. Rinse it completely before adding more bedding chips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.sugar-gliders.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/sugar-glider/&quot;&gt;Sugar Glider&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Skinny Pig]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/skinny-pig/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/skinny-pig</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/skinnypig-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo Credit: Geoff Robinson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skinny pigs are a cousin of the cute and familiar guinea pig. They are similar in terms of temperament and sociability, but they do require a bit 
more care due to the fact that they are, for the most part, hairless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sheltering a skinny pig is simple. They should be placed in a wire cage that has plenty of room for them to run around to cut down on the risk of obesity. Typically, these cages should be a minimum of 30x 18x 20 inches. 
The bottom of the cage should be coated in soft bedded pine chips, with a layer of fleece on the bottom of the cage to provide extra warmth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skinny pigs enjoy a variety of fruits and vegetables such as carrots, peppers, and zucchini.The majority of a skinny pig’s diet should consist of vitamin and protein fortified pellets that are marketed specifically for guinea pigs and skinny pigs. Skinny pigs should also be offered timothy hay to keep their teeth strong and provide supplemental vitamins for gastrointestinal health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since skinny pigs are typically more active during dusk and night hours, by having a large cage you can ensure that they are going to get as much exercise as they need. Skinny pigs can also be placed into a small rodent ball and allowed to roam around a safe area indoors. Typically, you would use a ball with a 10-12 inch circumference.
You can also allow your companion to roam around freely in a restricted, safe area. This can be accomplished by creating a safe zone using pet barriers that are marketed for small dogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest problems that face skinny pigs in terms of their health is that they are more susceptible to cuts and scrapes due to having little to no fur. Pay attention for cuts and abrasions and do not be afraid to consult a veterinarian if you are unsure of how to handle these situations.
Another common ailment to all small rodents is the overgrowth of their teeth. In order to combat this occurrence, you should give your skinny pig a chew toy or a log so that they can cull their teeth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should clean the bedding of your skinny pig’s habitat daily by removing all droppings and wet bedding. Each week you should completely change the bedding, and clean the bottom of the cage with a mixture of hot water and bleach. You can also use a small paint scraper to remove any droppings or bedding that is stuck to the bottom of the cage.Many skinny pigs enjoy the water, and can benefit greatly from a simple bath. However, you must be sure that their body temperature does not drop too low or they can become very ill. Make sure to have towels ready to warm your skinny pig after it has been cleaned, and then take it to a warm area before putting it back in the cage. If your skinny pig is able to hold still, you can use a hair dryer on a low setting to warm them up again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.baileesbeauties.weebly.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/skinny-pig/&quot;&gt;Skinny Pig&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Short Tailed Possum]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/short-tailed-possum/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/short-tailed-possum</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/possum-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short-tailed possums are famous for being one of the few truly insectivorous animals in the Americas. They are small, only three to six inches in length, and they do not have a pouch like most other marsupials. They are usually nocturnal, and can survive as your companion for up to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things to consider when raising a short-tailed possum is that they are solitary animals and should not be placed into a habitat with another animal.Typically, the best shelter for a short-tailed possum is a ten or twenty gallon aquarium with a mesh metal ceiling. This allows for good air circulation and all but removes the possibility that they will be able to escape. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom of the aquarium should be lined with soft wooden bedding such as aspen bedding or pine shavings. You should place a six inch circumference igloo or wooden box in the habitat so that the short-tailed possum can hide from the light during the daytime hours. Also, you should regulate the temperature in their enclosure between 75 and 85 degrees Fahrenheit to keep their body heat at acceptable levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since they are insectivores, you will need to provide your short-tailed possum with live crickets and mealworms for them to feed upon. 
You can also feed them soft foods that are made for ferrets. Short-tailed possums also enjoy eating ripe fruits such as apples, oranges, and grapes, though you should only feed it to them sparingly; once a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to exercise, the habitat should provide adequate space for the short-tailed possum to run around. However, they should be offered tubes made from PVC pipe or a similar material so that they can mimic the actions of moving through tunnels. It is not recommended to allow short-tailed possums to roam freely around the house at any time because they can easily become lost of squeeze into areas where they are difficult to safely retrieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the health concerns for short-tailed possums is their tails which are prehensile, but also prone to being injured by rubbing or chaffing.
In terms of their social health, your short-tailed possum should be allowed to climb on you to become accustomed to your scent so that they recognize you as a friend and companion. Like other small rodents, the respiratory system of short-tailed possums is very delicate, meaning that they should not be subjected to humid or cold areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is possible to bathe your short-tailed possum by hand, it is not recommended unless they have visible filth on their body because their lack of thick body hair makes them lose body heat quickly. If you must bathe your short-tailed possum, be sure to use a warm sponge and spend no more than five minutes cleaning your pet. When it comes to cleaning the habitat of the short-tailed possum, you should change the bedding every week and be sure to scrub the bottom of the aquarium with hot water. Also, be sure to clean your pet’s igloo and PVC tunnels every other week using nothing but hot water and a pipe cleaner. Short-tailed possums are very neat pets, and limit their waste to a single portion of their overall habitat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.sandsexoticanimals.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/short-tailed-possum/&quot;&gt;Short Tailed Possum&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Salamander]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/amphibians/salamander/"/>
  <id>/amphibians/salamander</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/alpine-newt-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salamanders are amphibians that usually range in length from a few 
inches up to several feet, though the average salamander is between 
four and eight inches long. They are famous for being able to regenerate 
damaged and missing limbs, to an extent, and for their lifespan of up to 
five years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salamanders must be kept in an aquarium, ten gallons is sufficient, 
because they require a moist environment. You should keep your 
salamander’s habitat between 65 and 75 degrees; room temperature. Be 
careful during the summer to make sure that the habitat is kept cool and 
out of direct sunlight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salamanders need to be kept in a habitat that has ample places to hide 
in darkness. This can be accomplished by adding artificial hollow logs, 
sticks, and vegetation which can all be purchased at a pet store or even 
a reptile and amphibian specialty store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to covering the bottom of the habitat, you should cover 
the floor with moss, potting compost, and bark chips to make it soft and 
similar to a salamander’s natural environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to place a pond in the habitat so that the salamander can 
remain moist and cool. You can purchase a porcelain bath from any pet 
store, but you must make sure that it is large enough to accommodate 
your salamander’s body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must keep in mind that salamanders are nocturnal, so you should 
typically feed them during nighttime hours. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salamanders are carnivorous and should be fed earthworms, slugs, 
woodlice, or crickets. You can purchase these in a pet store, but they are 
usually free-dried. If you want fresh ones, then you should find a local 
reptile and amphibian pet store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salamanders will get plenty of exercise inside of their habitat by running 
through the different obstacles that you place inside. They will also climb 
around the glass on the aquarium, but they will rarely try to escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you may be tempted to handle your salamander often, after all it is 
your pet and companion, you should actually handle them as little as 
possible. The salts and oils on your flesh are absorbed through their 
skin, and since they are such small creatures it can be harmful to their 
skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must clean your salamander’s habitat every two to three months. 
They are not very messy creatures so if you are vigilant about removing 
their droppings, you do not need to clean often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you clean the habitat, you should clean the glass with a mixture 
of warm, soapy water. You need to completely rinse all of the obstacles 
in the tank for cleaning, and you must completely replace the bottom 
mixture of moss or wood shavings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should clean the porcelain pond with hot water only, so that their 
bodies are not dried out by any remaining soap when it is finished. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.animalplanet.com/pets/how-to-care-for-
salamander.htm&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/amphibians/salamander/&quot;&gt;Salamander&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rat]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/rat/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/rat</id>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rat-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rats are one of the more atypical but neat small rodents that you can have as a pet. They are perfect for young children, and they come in a wide variety of color coats and temperaments. Typically, they live for between one and a half to two and a half years if they are cared for well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most other small rodents, rats are very social creatures. You should consider having at least two rats at any given time to prevent loneliness. When it comes to providing a living area for your rats, they should have a medium to large cage with bedding made from recycled paper or wood 
chips that are not pine or cedar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rats have a rather specialized diet that needs to be high in protein. There are “rat blocks” that are sold by various pet care companies that provide high protein as well as a large amount of vitamins and nutrients that will keep your rat healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should make sure that your rat has ample place to run around so that they do not become bored and lethargic. They enjoy playing with toys and 
tunneling in their bedding. You should also consider giving your rat man-made tunnels that they can use to avoid direct light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest dangers to the health of a rat is a cold. They are susceptible to them and if left untreated, they can be fatal. On the other end of the spectrum, rats are likely to be harmed by excessive amounts of heat, and should be kept in a moderately temperate room. If your rat becomes unusually lethargic, they should be examined by a vet, though there is not a great deal that they can do to treat an injured animal of this size.Rats require hard chewing blocks in order to keep their teeth from growing 
too large or creating dental problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While rats are small, and consequently so are their droppings, they need to have their cage or living space cleaned weekly. This will prevent diseases spreading between the two rats and allow them to live comfortably and cleanly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.ratcare.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/rat/&quot;&gt;Rat&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raccoon]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/raccoon/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/raccoon</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/raccoon-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raccoons are one of the most charming animals that you will have a chance to own. The term “chance” is important here, as some places require you to have a permit to own a raccoon. They are intelligent, loyal pets, but also have a tendency to be destructive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to providing shelter for a raccoon, you should be aware that they are free-roaming animals that do not like to be placed into cages. They are hardy animals and are about as likely to be injured by their environment as a cat or dog. They will roam around your home, but should be given some space that they can hide in during their sleeping hours.
You can also consider putting your raccoon in an outside pen. If you choose to put them in an outside pen, then it should be no smaller than a 7 foot square base with height of five feet. You should construct the pen out of chicken wire or similar metal mesh that would be difficult for them to chew through. However, it is usually not a good idea to switch them between inside and outside pets as it will affect their domesticity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to feed a raccoon, since they are not typical pets, is to give them a mixture of dry dog food as well as wet cat food. This should be mixed at a 1cup to ¼ can ratio.
Raccoons also enjoy fish and various types of vegetables such as zucchini, carrots, and celery. These dietary modifications will give them a boost of fiber that will help their digestive tract while providing them with a break from the monotony of kibble foods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your raccoon will be able to get as much exercise as it needs by running around your home. However, be forewarned that these animals tend to get into mischief during their adventures around their habitat and have been known to chew and shred household rugs and furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All raccoons that are made to be pets should be spayed or neutered not long after they are brought home. However, one of the greatest difficulties associated with a raccoon is the fact that there are few veterinarians that will treat raccoons for legal and safety reasons. Be sure to find and consult a veterinarian in your area before you bring home a raccoon. Another consideration for the health of your raccoon is their teeth. While they do not need to cull them like a rat or guinea pig, raccoons need to have a diet that is rich in calcium to fortify their teeth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best parts about owning a raccoon is that they can be house- broken and trained to use a litter box like a cat. You can use a cat’s litter box for a raccoon, as well as cat litter which requires weekly cleaning at the minimum. Also, you should clean the base of the litter box once a week with a mixture of half a cup of bleach to one gallon of water to kill germs and bacteria.
Raccoons love being in and around water, so they can be bathed regularly for fun and for hygiene. You can wash them in warm water using baby shampoo to clean their fur. For the most part raccoons will be complacent in water and allow you to easily clean them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.sybilsden.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/raccoon/&quot;&gt;Raccoon&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prairie Dog]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/prairie-dog/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/prairie-dog</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/prairie-dog-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most fun and unique animals that you can have as a pet is a prairie dog. While they are small, only about the size of a large squirrel, they are incredibly hardy animals with an average lifespan between ten and twelve years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shelter that you will want to use to house your prairie dog is a multi-level ferret cage. These tend to be up to three feet tall with base dimensions of two feet by two feet. You will want to use a wife mesh cage to ensure that they will not escape easily, as they are very capable escape artists.
You should cover the bottom of the cage in hay or pine shavings so that 
moisture can be absorbed, and also so that the prairie dog can create a burrow. 
Speaking of burrows and nests, prairie dogs can get bored of a single housing, so you should consider having a spare cage or open area in your home where you can let it roam freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main diet of a prairie dog should consist of a mixture of hay and specially formulated rodent blocks that can be found in any pet store. 
In order to supplement their vitamins and nutrients, you should also feed your prairie dog a variety of fruits and vegetables along with an ample supply of water inside of a feeder bottle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise is very important to prairie dogs since their metabolism is only about half of that of other small rodents such as guinea pigs and chinchillas. This is one of the reasons that they are so hardy; they store energy well and use it sparingly.
You can encourage your prairie dog to be active by keeping it stimulated. Give it plenty of toy balls in their cage, and be sure to let them out if the environment allows. Also, provide a means for them to burrow, after all it comes naturally to them and is a great source of exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of biggest health problems that can occur in Prairie dogs is obesity. Since their metabolism is slow, they burn energy slowly. Therefore, you should make sure not to overfeed your prairie dog not matter how much it will beg you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the social health of your prairie dog, you should be sure to initiate bonding with them as soon as you bring them home. This can bedone by holding them for twenty minutes at a time, so they accept you as a companion as well as an authority figure. This will prevent malcontent throughout their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic grooming of your prairie dog can be done by washing them in a tub with tepid water and baby shampoo. This will clean their fur of droppings which tend to stick to them when they burrow in their own mess. You should clean the bedding out of the cage every week while cleaning the bottom of the cage with hot water only. Prairie dogs have a tendency to be very sensitive to small amounts of chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.sandsexoticanimals.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/prairie-dog/&quot;&gt;Prairie Dog&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mudpuppy]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/amphibians/mudpuppy/"/>
  <id>/amphibians/mudpuppy</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mudpuppies are a species of salamander that starts their lifecycle as a 
tadpole and are completely aquatic, meaning that they spend the vast majority 
of their time in the water. While they are easy to care for if you have the 
proper provisions, they are also nocturnal meaning that they are usually only 
awake at night. This is an exotic pet and good for those who have the time 
and money to spend on them. They will grow to about 17 inches and then live 
for anywhere between 10 and 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Habitat is one of the most important aspects of owning a mudpuppy. You 
should start by getting a large aquarium, at least 20 gallons. This will need 
to be filed almost to the top, with two-thirds of the tank filled with water 
to prevent spillage. This water should be as close to 7.0 ph as possible, 
even if it means buying spring water. Use ph testing strips to test the 
water, and use acidifiers or bases to adjust it as needed, but consult a 
reptile and amphibian pet store beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom of the habitat should be filled with gravel and other small 
rocks. You should also use driftwood, real or artificial, in order to give 
the mudpuppy a nice hiding space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water should be kept between the temperatures of 55 and 70 degrees. Make 
sure that you own a thermometer to check the temperature frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will also need a filtration system that is gated to prevent injuring 
your mudpuppy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mudpuppies prefer to have live food, and they are carnivores. They will 
survive comfortably on snails, larvae, and worms. You can also give them 
feeder fish such as minnows. The best part about feeding them minnows is that 
you can leave them in the tank and allow your mudpuppy decide when to eat 
them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since they are aquatic animals, mudpuppies will spend most of their day 
swimming around, giving them all of the exercise that they need. Do not take 
your mudpuppy out of the water to handle it, they will suffocate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest health concerns regarding mudpuppies is keeping the water 
clean. Bacteria thrive in water, and it can spread to your mudpuppy quickly. 
You need to find an exotic pet specialist that can help your mudpuppy if it 
becomes ill, as most veterinarians are not equipped to help mudpuppies or 
other amphibians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consideration for the health of female mudpuppies is that they will 
lay eggs throughout their life that needs to be properly disposed of after 
they are laid. You can expect them to lay between 30 and 100 eggs a year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to cleaning the habitat, remove large debris daily and check 
the water filter.
Every 2 or 3 months, you must clean the entire habitat. You should use hot 
soapy water to clean the tank glass. Make sure that you rinse it in hot water 
when you are finished to remove the leftover soap. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replace the rocks in the habitat completely, and change the wood if it is 
real. Clean the artificial wood with hot water only. When you are finished, 
replace the water with the same type of water that you used to fill it 
initially. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.caudata.org/cc/species/Necturus/N_maculosus.shtml&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/amphibians/mudpuppy/&quot;&gt;Mudpuppy&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mouse]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/mouse/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/mouse</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mouse-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice are a nice starter pet for anyone looking for a small companion. They are small, easy to care for, and can be very social or independent pets. Mice are also fragile, and must be treated carefully when they are handled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like rats and other small animals, mice are very social within their own species, so it is not a bad idea to keep more than one mouse at a time. You can keep mice in a small, ten gallon glass aquarium with a wire mesh roof. They do not require the extensive air flow that other small rodentsneed, and the glass will prevent them from gnawing on a wire cage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice can typically subsist on commercial mouse pellets, but make sure that they have a good source of natural protein.You can also feed your mouse some fruit and vegetables in small amounts such as peas, carrots, and bananas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside of their aquarium, mice will be able to get adequate exercise. However, you should consider getting them some tubes to run though for entertainment purposes. If you hand-tame your mouse, you can allow them to run around a small, enclosed area in your home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the health issues that are common to mice is their teeth overgrowing. You must provide a chewing block or toy so that they can keep their teeth healthy and culled. Mice are susceptible to lice and other skin parasites. If you suspect that they are infested, take them to a veterinarian immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you can brush their hair, most mice will not sit still long enough until they are trained. When you are handling your mouse, you must be careful not to grab them by the end of their tail to avoid injury. Mice are fragile, so be sure to supervise any children that are going to handle them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.humanesociety.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/mouse/&quot;&gt;Mouse&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Iguana]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/reptiles/iguana/"/>
  <id>/reptiles/iguana</id>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/iguana-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iguanas can be a fun and relatively low key pet option. However, they can also be fairly expensive, especially when buying initial supplies for the pet. Getting a new iguana can be very exciting, but it’s important to leave the iguana alone for a few weeks after brining it home, in order for it to adjust properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iguanas should have a cage or other type of enclosure. Some iguana owners allow their iguanas to have free range of the home, but if this is your first time owning an iguana, it’s best to have it in a cage at first. Iguanas can grow very large, and the cage should be at least twice the length of the iguana, and owners may need to get a larger cage as the iguana grows. The cage should be lined with newspapers, paper towels, or carpet. There should also be climbing structures or shelves so the iguana can climb and explore. Iguana also needs to have regular exposure to natural sunlight in addition to a heat lamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to general iguana food that can be purchased at a pet store, iguanas also need fruits and vegetables. Iguanas should be fed at least once per day, and more for iguanas that have larger appetites. Fresh water should also be easily accessible, and you can spray water onto the iguana’s food in order to ensure it’s drinking enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure not to handle the iguana during the first few weeks of having it. As the iguana gets used to his new surroundings, you can handle it more and more, and it will become more tame. Having it out of the cage, under close supervision, is alright once he’s gotten used to his home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep the iguana healthy, regular cleaning is necessary. The iguana owner should also use antibacterial soap to thoroughly clean his or her hands after feeding or otherwise handling the iguana. The cage should be cleaned regularly, and the bedding should be removed. It’s a good idea to invest in a disinfectant that will sterilize the cage during regular cleanings. Remove the iguana while cleaning the cage. Regular cleaning will help avoid parasites and other diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, iguanas are fairly clean, but you should regularly give your iguana a bath to clean off food or feces on the animal. You can purchase a large tub to use for a bath, and it should be filled with warm water. Soap should never be used. The iguana cage should also be lightly sprayed with water from a spray bottle on a daily basis, to keep the habitat moist.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reptiles/iguana/&quot;&gt;Iguana&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hedgehog]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/hedgehog/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/hedgehog</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hedgehog-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedgehogs are relatively small, insect-eating rodents that can make great pets if they have a dedicated owner. While many people will be turned away by the presence of their quills, hedgehogs are able to be petted safely, without any risk of injury to you or them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shelter that you need to provide for your hedgehog will need to be very large to accommodate their active lifestyle. You should have a multi-tiered cage that has a two square feet base and at least two feet high. They require a great deal of space to move about. The bottom of their cage, usually a wire cage, should not be covered solely by wood chip bedding. They should have some sort of loose cloth such as fleece that they can wrap themselves in if they feel cold, as they are very sensitive to changes in temperature. For the most part, hedgehogs do not like to share their habitat with other hedgehogs and should be kept as solo pets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedgehogs have unusual dietary requirements that must be met if they are to live a healthy life. While they can be fed dry cat food with a high protein and vitamin D content, they can also subsist on freeze-dried beetles. Make sure the food bowl is wide enough that the hedgehog will not turn it over while they are attempting to eat. Pet shops carry ceramic bowls that are extra wide and have a firm base that are perfect for 
hedgehogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, you can allow your hedgehog out of its cage to get To help them get exercise, you can use pet barriers to block off a room so exercise in a safe indoor area. They usually do not like to be placed into balls, depending on their temperament, and they prefer open spaces to their cage, no matter how large it may be, that they can frolic safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most unique problem facing hedgehogs is obesity. You must make sure that they have adequate space to move around in the cage. Also, you must be sure that you regulate their diet so that they do not eat too much food. If your hedgehog is unable to fold into a ball, then you should consult a veterinarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other pet, you should change the bedding in your hedgehog’s cage every week. Since they prefer cloth material, you should clean any droppings out of the cage daily, and be prepared to change the bedding at any time. You can wash the fleece in a washing machine or by hand, using only dish soap and hot water to prevent skin irritation. When it comes to cleaning the base of the cage, you should use hot water and dish soap in conjunction with a scrubbing brush for maximum cleanliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.hedgehogclub.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/hedgehog/&quot;&gt;Hedgehog&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guinea Pig]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/guinea-pig/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/guinea-pig</id>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/guinea-pig-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most loving and rewarding pets that you can own is a Guinea Pig. They are quiet, easy to care for, and can provide companionship for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary shelter that you can provide for a Guinea Pig is a large cage with soft bedding. However, many pet owners prefer to let their Guinea Pigs roam around their home, either freely or inside a play ball. Certain precautions must be taken to ensure that your pet does not wander into any hazardous areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you will primarily feed a Guinea Pig manufactured food, you can always supplement their diet with vegetables such as carrots to make sure that they receive the proper amount of nutrients and vitamins to allow them to live a long, healthy life. One of the treats that you can feed Guinea Pigs is timothy hay, a healthy grass that allows them to keep their teeth healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Guinea Pigs will spend the majority of their day in an area of the cage that is out of direct sight. Some Guinea Pigs will remain nocturnal when you keep them and should be given a dark shelter. For this reason you need to make sure that you pay attention to when your pet is most active, and allow them to wander out of the cage freely under supervision, or inside a ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most other small animals, you need to make sure that your Guinea Pig is drinking sufficient amounts of water. This is most noticeable in their droppings, which should be small and relatively hard. If they experience wetness in their hindquarters or have any noticeable discharge, then they 
need to be taken to a vet immediately for examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleaning a Guinea Pig’s fur is simple because they enjoy water, for the most part. However, this is discouraged in the winter or in a cold environment. They must be bathed in warm water to regulate their body temperature. Also, since they frequently defecate, it is smart to clean their cage or primary area before you can smell it. Try not to put a clean Guinea Pig into a dirty area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.aspca.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/guinea-pig/&quot;&gt;Guinea Pig&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gerbil]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/gerbil/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/gerbil</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/gerbil-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerbils are one of the most active and lovable small rodents that you can keep as a pet. That also means that they can be some of the most troublesome to keep in a cage. However, if you manage to give them a good home, then your gerbil can live for between three and four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other small rodents, gerbils are very social animals and you should at least consider keeping several of them together. However, it is a bad idea 
to keep males and females together because they will breed quickly. You can house gerbils in a wire cage or a glass aquarium. It needs to be kept away from direct light or cold air to avoid sickness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerbils tend to eat seeds as a main source of food. You can buy a pre-mixed blend of food at any pet store that will consist of seed, pellets, and dried vegetables. You can feed gerbils small amounts of fresh fruits and vegetables. Also, they enjoy sunflower seeds as a snack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not advised to let your gerbils out of their cage and into the open unless you are absolutely sure that the area is escape proof. Gerbils are very frisky, and they can squeeze into small areas and become lost. Another great way to make sure that your gerbil gets exercise is by putting them in a small exercise ball and letting them loose around your home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most gerbils should be taken to a veterinarian once a year for examination. One of the biggest dangers facing gerbils is actually diarrhea and dehydration. This can be prevented by providing adequate water and fiber-rich foods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any pet that is kept in a cage, you should change the bedding of your gerbil’s habitat every week, with daily removal of droppings. It is important that your pets develop a sense of familiarity with you. This can be achieved by handling them safely, and often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt; *Source: http://www.aspca.org *&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/gerbil/&quot;&gt;Gerbil&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gecko]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/reptiles/gecko/"/>
  <id>/reptiles/gecko</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/leopard-gecko-2.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geckos make one of the easiest types of reptiles to have as a pet. There are many different breeds of geckos, though the leopard gecko is likely one of the most common and popular breeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geckos should be kept in an terrarium. A 10 gallon terrarium is appropriate for one or two geckos, though larger terrariums can be used as well, and if you have more than two, you should strongly consider having a larger terrarium. The terrarium should also have a screen lid. The terrarium should have sand in the bottom, and be sure to use sand that is safe for animals; industrial sand or sand that contains a large amount of dust can be dangerous. Geckos will also need a heat lamp or heat pad of some sort, as they’re cold blooded. Be sure to also keep a few things in the terrarium for the gecko to hid under, such as a small cardboard box or a small plastic container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geckos typically eat live prey, typically crickets or mealworms are used. Crickets are very nutritious, but you need to be careful to ensure they don’t get out. Mealworms are less likely to escape, and are easier to keep for a long amount of time. There are also various vitamins that can be given to geckos to add to the nutrition they’re getting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geckos that are fed crickets are able to gain some additional activity, as crickets are more stimulating and can provide activity for the geckos when they feed. Otherwise, geckos do not need major additional exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not grab a gecko by its tail, as it will lose its tail as a defense mechanism. The tail will grow back, but avoid this whenever possible. Geckos can also be susceptible to parasites and mites. Be sure to regularly clean their terrarium and get rid of any uneaten food on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geckos do shed their skin, so this is something gecko owners need to be aware of. Young geckos will shed more frequently, and the gecko’s skin will turn dull and a white color right before shedding. At this time, it’s important to keep the terrarium moist to help with the shedding process. Be sure to keep a small portion of the terrarium moist, especially during the shedding process.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reptiles/gecko/&quot;&gt;Gecko&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Terrestrial Frog]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/amphibians/frog/"/>
  <id>/amphibians/frog</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/frog-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terrestrial frogs, land dwellers, are the type of frog that is easiest to 
raise, and are the best type of frog for those who have never cared for 
an amphibian before. For those who enjoy these spunky critters, you will 
be happy to know that the average terrestrial frog in captivity lives for ten 
to twelve years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important aspects of caring for a terrestrial frog is the 
habitat that you provide. If you get your frog young, then you can put it 
into a 5 gallon aquarium and then move it to a 10 gallon aquarium as it 
grows. Feel free to begin with the 10 gallon aquarium if you have one 
available. Be sure to place a wire screen over the top of the aquarium, 
because they can and will jump out of the habitat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to provide a UV light for your frog, since they will not be 
sunning outside. This will mimic the natural sunlight, providing them with 
warmth while stimulating their bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should put a small amount of sticks and hollow logs into the habitat 
to give your frog a place to hide, climb and sleep. The bottom of the 
habitat should be covered in a smooth gravel mixture that can be found 
in any pet store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there is no ìFrog foodî for sale, you need to pay close attention to 
your frogís diet. Terrestrial frogs prefer live food such as crickets or 
mealworms. You can buy these at any pet store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to feeding your frog, you must understand that they do 
not need to be fed every day. Some days they may eat one or more 
crickets a day, and other days they will just not be interested in eating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to provide a fresh pond of water for your frog to “drink”. They 
will sit in the water pond, so you need to make sure that the pond is 
almost as wide as your frog. If you are feeling unsure, consult a worker 
at a pet store and they can recommend a pond for your frog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, frogs will get all of the exercise that they need inside 
of their habitat, but that does not mean that you cannot or should not 
take them out of their cage. However, you must be careful when you 
remove your frog from their habitat because they are tricky to catch once 
they get loose. Make sure that you can limit their area of movement in a 
small room, and let them loose, under close supervision, once or twice a 
week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary health concern for terrestrial frogs is that they can carry 
diseases home from the pet store and possibly infect other members of 
their living area. Since frogs are tough creatures, do not expect them to 
ìshowî when they are becoming ill. Typically, when frogs show that they 
are ill, they are already sick and tend to have a fast downturn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to check around your area to see if there are any 
veterinarians that will take care of frogs, since they are considered 
exotic. You need to know where you can go if your friend becomes ill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleaning the habitat is both important and somewhat difficult. After all, a 
wet area is the perfect breeding ground for bacteria that can make your 
frog ill. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clean the water pond every other day, no exceptions. Clean the bottom 
of the pond with hot water only because chemicals left over will be 
absorbed through the skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleaning the stone can be done in the same way; use boiling water to 
clean the rocks once a week and then change the rocks completely once 
a month. Also, change the sticks and logs once a month, or buy artificial 
ones and clean them once a month using the same method as cleaning 
the stones, with boiling water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: Terrestrial Frog: http://www.frogdaze.com/caring_for_your_frog.html&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/amphibians/frog/&quot;&gt;Terrestrial Frog&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ferret]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/ferret/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/ferret</id>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ferret-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferrets are some of the most beautiful and interesting small, domesticated rodents. They come in a wide variety of colors including brown, red, white, and gold. They typically live between six and eight years, and require a bit of special care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since ferrets are some of the most active and playful small rodents, they need a great deal of space to move around. As such, they should not be caged for long periods of time, and when they are, they need a cage that has plenty of tubes and hiding spaces to keep themselves entertained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since ferrets are some of the most active and playful small rodents, they need a great deal of space to move around. As such, they should not be caged for long periods of time, and when they are, they need a cage that has plenty of tubes and hiding spaces to keep themselves entertained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferrets are one of the most playful small rodents. They need to have a great deal of time to run around every day or they will get restless and start chewing on anything that they can find. This can cause injuries and aggravation. So, it is important to have a small rodent ball that you can put your ferret into so that they can roll around safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most dangerous illness that can face a ferret is intestinal obstruction. This happens when they chew on soft plastic pieces such as their food bowl, and swallow it, creating a blockage that is often fatal. Also, you may want to consider de-scenting your ferret for practical reasons, unless you are breeding your ferret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should change your ferret’s bedding completely at least once a week, with daily removals of wet or messy bedding. Also, it is possible to litter train ferrets since they are such intelligent animals. Not only will this give them a cleaner habitat, but it will ensure that they live a longer, healthier life. Not to mention, it is a neat trick that you can show your friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/ferret/&quot;&gt;Ferret&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chipmunk]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/chipmunk/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/chipmunk</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/chipmunk-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siberian chipmunks are fun, active critters that can be a bit of a handful to raise because of their high energy. They are small, typically between five and six inches in length, and only weigh about 2-3 ounces. Despite their small size and active lifestyle, Siberian chipmunks can live for up to ten years if they are treated properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The housing for a Siberian chipmunk is one of the more complicated facets of owning a chipmunk. They should have a multi-level wire cage. The bars should be less than a half inch apart to prevent them from escaping from the habitat.
While they are small animals, the cage should measure 12x24x18 inches at minimum. This will allow them to have plenty of room to run around, especially considering that it is not recommended that you allow them to run around your home. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another neat idea for a chipmunk housing unit is to build a small wooden enclosure that is about the size of a birdhouse: 6x6x8 inches for example. This will give them the sense of being in an outdoors area while providing a dark place within their cage.The bedding in their habitat should consist of a thick assortment of wood chips that can be burrowed in while providing a soft landing area for when 
they tumble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main part of a Siberian chipmunk’s diet should consist of rodent diet pellets that are high in fiber and protein. Chipmunks should also be fed a large assortment of vegetables, fruits, and nuts such as pecans, peanuts, apples, grapes, and broccoli. Siberian chipmunks require fresh water to be added to their bottle daily. This should be cleaned at least once every two weeks with a pipe brush and hot water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, Siberian chipmunks will be able to get as much exercise as they need in their cage as long as you provide them with a wheel and a large enough cage. You should also purchase several toys to keep your chipmunk engaged and playful such as logs and balls that they can roll through their bedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the health concerns for Siberian chipmunks is the length of their nails. You should take your chipmunk to a vet at least once a year, and during that time they should have their nails trimmed to an acceptable level.Another consideration for Siberian chipmunk health is oral care. You should provide plenty of chewing toys so that they can cull their teeth, which will prevent oral decay and a variety of other ailments. You should watch for signs of a cold such as runny eyes and coughing. This can lead to complications of the respiratory system, which is one of the leading causes of death in chipmunks besides old age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can give a Siberian chipmunk a sponge bath if they become too dirty from walking through soiled bedding. Use only warm water and be extremely gentle. You should change the bedding of the cage once a week and clean the bottom of the cage at the same time. To do this, you should use only hot water and a scrub brush so that there are no adverse reactions to cleaning chemicals. By following these simple tips, you can extend the life of your Siberian chipmunk by years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.sandsexoticanimals.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/chipmunk/&quot;&gt;Chipmunk&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chinchilla]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small-animals/chinchilla/"/>
  <id>/small-animals/chinchilla</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/chinchilla-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinchillas are a medium-sized rodent, between ten and twelve inches in length, and are famous for their love of burrowing and hiding in their habitats. They make great pets because they are soft, social, and rarely bite. Aside from their beauty, they can live as long as twenty years if they receive the right kind of care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shelter that you are going to want to give your chinchilla is similar to other small rodents in the sense that you should provide a wire cage with a plastic basin. However, it must be larger than the typical rodent cage and should measure somewhere around 2 feet by 1 ½ feet by 2 feet. They need a cage where they can have room to run, jump, and hide themselves as well as their toys. Like other small animals, they benefit from having bedding such as pine chips on the bottom of their cage to catch waste and soften their landings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can feed chinchillas a blend of pellets specially made for chinchillas that is sold in any pet store. Also, chinchillas enjoy timothy hay and other small animal-safe grasses. It is important to keep a feeder of fresh, temperate water in their cage at all times. Chinchillas need to drink frequently, and should have their bottles cleaned regularly. You can clean their bottles by using hot water and a small amount of dish soap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since chinchillas tend to become very attached to their owners or other chinchillas in their habitat, you should dedicate time every day to interacting and playing with your chinchilla. They are fragile animals, but they enjoy running, climbing, and jumping.You can put your chinchilla in a small rodent ball, one foot in circumference, and allow them to roam around a safe area. Chinchillas can also roam freely, but you must be sure that the area is devoid of cubbies or other areas where they can become lost or trapped. You can buy several mesh gates that will allow you to cordon off a room 
for your chinchilla to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are cared for properly, chinchillas can live an incredibly long life for a rodent. This requires a yearly checkup with a veterinarian to look for any possible anomalies. One of the most common injuries that chinchillas can suffer is a broken bone in their back foot that can result from rough play or fighting with other chinchillas. By keeping a thick layer of soft bedding, you can reduce the risk of this happening. Another consideration for chinchillas’ health is gastrointestinal problems that can result from an improper diet. If your chinchilla seems unusually lethargic or is laying down much more than usual, they should be taken to a vet immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things that you can do for your chinchilla is to give them a clean environment. Make sure that you remove droppings and wet bedding daily, and completely replace the bedding once every week. It is important to clean the bottom of the basin out using hot water and hypoallergenic dish soap such as Dawn that will not provoke adverse skin reactions. Use a scrub brush to get a complete cleaning experience. You can give your chinchilla a bath if they begin to smell badly, but be sure to use temperate water rather than hot or cold water because they are very sensitive to changes in temperature. To bathe them, use a small amount of water and consider putting your chinchilla in a colander or sieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: http://www.chinchillacare.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small-animals/chinchilla/&quot;&gt;Chinchilla&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bearded Dragon]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/reptiles/bearded-dragon/"/>
  <id>/reptiles/bearded-dragon</id>
  <published>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bearded-dragon-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons are a fun, entertaining type of reptile to have as a pet, though they do require special equipment and some extra attention compared to many other types of reptiles. However, they are also fairly active, and are relatively easy to tame, making them enjoyable pets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons require fairly large tanks; a 40 gallon tank is the smallest acceptable size for a single beaded dragon, and if you have more than one, they should have a bigger tank. It’s also necessary to have a screen lid to cover the top of the lid. The cage should be lined with paper towels or paper, though sand, wood shavings, and similar products should be avoided, as the animal may eat them. The cage should also be complete with rocks and things to hide in. Most importantly, beaded dragons need exposure to heat lamps, and special UVA/UVB radiation lamps for reptiles can be purchased. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons should have water provided at all times. Their diet consists of both insects and vegetables. They typically eat crickets or mealworms, and younger bearded dragons should be fed more frequently, twice each day. Adults can be fed just once each day. Vegetables such as carrots, green beans, and peas can also be fed to bearded dragons .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons can be handled regularly by their owners. Though they don’t need excessive regular attention, bearded dragons can be handled in order to give them extra activity. Some owners get leashes for bearded dragons so that they can explore without worry that they’ll get away. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bearded dragons may get dehydrated, so it’s important to keep water readily available. Bearded dragons with sunken eyes or wrinkled skin are likely dehydrated. Additional water or a diluted sports drink can be administered with an eye dropper if they initially refuse water. Bearded dragons also may 
experience droopy eyes, which is often caused by kidney problems. A bearded dragon with droopy eyes should see a vet right away for treatment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though bearded dragons do not require extensive grooming, their nails may get long and extremely sharp. Owners can use a nail clipper and trip the tips of the nails, being careful not to trim too deeply. Nails should be trimmed no more than once every month.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reptiles/bearded-dragon/&quot;&gt;Bearded Dragon&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
