<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Crittergo</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2014-02-15T14:28:19-08:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Crittergo</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rabbit]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small%20animal/rabbit/"/>
  <id>/small%20animal/rabbit</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-14T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rabbit-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the cutest and most engaging small animals that you can own is a rabbit. Domesticated rabbits vary in looks and personality, 
each with their own benefits. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, you should keep your rabbit at home in a large, comfortable cage with a great deal of soft bedding for them to 
nuzzle. They should always be kept indoors, as they are social animals and can be literally driven to a heart attack if they see a predator coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of a domesticated rabbit’s diet should come from grasses and timothy hay. These nutritious grasses are crucial to keep your rabbit’s digestive system and teeth healthy. If you are raising your rabbit from a young age, then for the first year you should give them a great deal of fresh, plain rabbit pellets. It is also important to keep an ample supply of water in a dish or a feeder, depending on which one your rabbit prefers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your rabbit will need a large amount of space to run around and frolic, but again this needs to be indoors only. You need to rabbit-proof the area to prevent them from chewing paper or electrical wires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you are keeping a single rabbit, then you should consider spaying and neutering them to prevent certain types of cancer from 
forming. Typically, you should take your rabbit for a checkup once every year. Like other small rodents, if you notice that your rabbit is not moving its bowels regularly, then you should take it to the vet immediately to check for obstruction. This is prevalent in small animals, like rabbits, that like to chew household materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should remove all of the soiled bedding from your rabbit’s cage every single day, with a full cleaning occurring once a week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see your rabbit eating their own feces, do not be concerned. This is a normal activity that is used to help regulate their bowels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rabbits should be brushed often to help maintain their fur. When picking your rabbit up, support its rear as well as its head.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small%20animal/rabbit/&quot;&gt;Rabbit&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 14, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hedgehog]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small%20animals/hedgehog/"/>
  <id>/small%20animals/hedgehog</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-14T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hedgehog-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedgehogs are relatively small, insect-eating rodents that can make great pets if they have a dedicated owner. While many people will be turned away by the presence of their quills, hedgehogs are able to be petted safely, without any risk of injury to you or them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shelter that you need to provide for your hedgehog will need to bevery large to accommodate their active lifestyle. You should have a multi-tiered cage that has a two square feet base and at least two feet high. They require a great deal of space to move about. The bottom of their cage, usually a wire cage, should not be covered solely by wood chip bedding. They should have some sort of loose cloth such as fleece that they can wrap themselves in if they feel cold, as they are very sensitive to changes in temperature. For the most part, hedgehogs do not like to share their habitat with other hedgehogs and should be kept as solo pets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedgehogs have unusual dietary requirements that must be met if they are to live a healthy life. While they can be fed dry cat food with a high protein and vitamin D content, they can also subsist on freeze-dried beetles. 
Make sure the food bowl is wide enough that the hedgehog will not turn it over while they are attempting to eat. Pet shops carry ceramic bowls that are extra wide and have a firm base that are perfect for hedgehogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most part, you can allow your hedgehog out of its cage to get exercise in a safe indoor area. They usually do not like to be placed into balls, depending on their temperament, and they prefer open spaces to their cage, no matter how large it may be. To help them get exercise, you can use pet barriers to block off a room so that they can frolic safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most unique problem facing hedgehogs is obesity. You must make sure that they have adequate space to move around in the cage. Also, you must be sure that you regulate their diet so that they do not eat too much food. If your hedgehog is unable to fold into a ball, then you should consult a veterinarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other pet, you should change the bedding in your hedgehog’s cage every week. Since they prefer cloth material, you should clean any droppings out of the cage daily, and be prepared to change the bedding at any time. You can wash the fleece in a washing machine or by hand, using only dish soap and hot water to prevent skin irritation. When it comes to cleaning the base of the cage, you should use hot water and dish soap in conjunction with a scrubbing brush for maximum&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt; &lt;em&gt;Source: http://hedgehogclub.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small%20animals/hedgehog/&quot;&gt;Hedgehog&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 14, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chameleon]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/reptile/chameleon/"/>
  <id>/reptile/chameleon</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-14T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/chameleon-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people like the idea of a chameleon as a pet due to their ability to change colors. 
Chameleons are hardy, and don’t require a great deal of care. However, they aren’t 
particularly playful or cuddly, and they should not be handled regularly, so for pet owners 
who want more interaction, they aren’t the best choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chameleons need fairly large aquariums that are well ventilated; ideally made out 
of screen as opposed to glass. The cage should be lined with a light bedding, like 
newspaper or paper towels. Things like sand or gravel are not good ideas, as the 
chameleons may eat it and have health problems. A heat lamp is also required for 
chameleons. It’s important for the cage to contain live plants, branches, and other 
similar item so the chameleons are able to climb and exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chameleons can eat a wide range of different types of foods, from insects such as 
crickets or worms, to various plants, including lettuce, flowering plants, dandelion leaves, 
and carrots. Insects that are too large could be difficult to digest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chameleons can become stressed if they are handled too much. However, while 
cleaning the cage, owners can give chameleons time to explore and climb. A small, 
enclosed, alternate cage can be used to give the chameleon more space during 
cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chameleons are prone to getting dehydrated, so it’s a good idea to regularly mist the 
cage with a water bottle to keep the enclosure moist. A dehydrated chameleon may 
have closed or sunken eyes. Be sure the chameleon is getting regular water. By misting 
regularly, you can ensure your chameleon has plenty of water, as misting allows for 
water droplets to form on the plants in the cage for the chameleon to drink. A clean 
spray bottle is the easiest way to keep water in the cage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chameleons do not require any significant cleaning or groom, and in fact, handling of &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;chameleons should be limited. They are extremely low maintenance in this respect.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reptile/chameleon/&quot;&gt;Chameleon&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 14, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cats]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/cats/cat/"/>
  <id>/cats/cat</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-14T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cat-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cat is a great option for anyone looking for a pet that is both fun and friendly, yet requires 
relatively low care. While cats certainly need love and attention, in addition to food, water, 
and their litter boxes regularly cleaned, they are also quite independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats do not require any specific types of shelter, though many cat owners purchase various “cat condos” or similar products that serve as a place for cats to nap and play. Such products often include a scratching component as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats typically can be fed either wet or dry cat food, and should always have plenty of fresh water available. Cat treats can also be incorporated, though they should be limited to ensure your cat doesn’t gain too much weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kittens are often full of energy and enjoy playing, and keeping plenty of toys available will ensure the cat does a lot of playing to burn off energy. Cats who spend time outdoors likely get more exercise than indoor cats. To ensure your cat stays healthy and doesn’t gain too much weight, do not overfeed and take time each day to play with your cat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats are generally quite healthy, but be sure to check with a vet if you notice anything out of the ordinary. Hairballs can be a common problem,, but there are many products that can be purchased to avoid them. As cats age, there are several health problems that can take place, so pay special attention to aging cats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats are fairly self-sufficient when it comes to grooming. Short haired cats require minimal grooming, though long haired cats can be brushed on occasions to reduce shedding. Brushing can also help lower the risk of your cat experiencing hairballs.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/cats/cat/&quot;&gt;Cats&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 14, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hamster]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/small%20animal/hamster/"/>
  <id>/small%20animal/hamster</id>
  <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2014-02-11T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Crittergo</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>crittergo@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hamster-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to own a small pet, a hamster is a good place to start. They require minimal care when in a comfortable environment. They are nocturnal and prefer to live alone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shelter&quot;&gt;Shelter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many styles of shelter for your hamster, from cages, aquariums, to intricate habitats with a number of tubes to crawl through. Once you’ve chosen the a type of housing, you will need to fill it with bedding to keep the environment dry and keep odor under control.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Store-bought hamster foods include a mixture of seeds and grains. For added variety, you can supplement with fresh nuts, fruits and vegetables a couple times a week. Avoid onions, candy, chocolate, large beans, rhubarb or raw potatoes. Always have have plenty of fresh water in a suspended rodent drinking bottle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activityexercise&quot;&gt;Activity/Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamsters like to burrow and exercise. A shelter with tubes and spaces to hide in and a wheel to run around will keep your hamster happy and healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While hamsters are normally quite hardy, small injuries or illnesses can complicate quickly. If you find signs such as loss of appetite, sneezing, discharge from the nose or eyes, wheezing, wetness around the tail, hair loss, or diarrhea you should consider a trip to the vet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grooming&quot;&gt;Grooming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your hamster cage will require touching up or bedding replacement. If you notice stronger odors, consider cleaning more frequently. 
Unless your hamster has something sticky in its fur, it should never have a bath in water. Fill a small bowl with chinchilla bath sand made from volcanic ash and place it in the cage. The hamster will instinctively roll around in it to clean itself off. Make sure that the sand you purchase is dust-free to prevent respiratory issues. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/small%20animal/hamster/&quot;&gt;Hamster&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Crittergo at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Crittergo&lt;/a&gt; on February 11, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
